today I'm going to be showing
self-taught students like yourself
everything you need to know to thrive at
learning piano and to accomplish this
I'm going to be sharing with you
learning resources equipment you're
going to need how to practice
objectively and then we're going to wrap
it all together with a road map so that
your path forward is Crystal Clear one
of the first learning resources you're
going to want to be aware of is a piano
lesson book one of the reasons these are
so great is that they introduce you to
topics and pieces in order from the very
beginning which is a great structured
way of learning where these fall a
little flat is you don't get
instructional videos or a teacher with
them so if you don't understand the
lesson in the page or two it gives you
well you're kind of out of luck but
either way if you have a teacher or not
this is a great resource to have because
it's great to have supplementary pieces
to play in order of difficulty and these
are great for that I highly recommend
this one this is the Alfred adult
all-in-one piano course and I also
recommend Now searching through my book
catalog here home and unfortunately I
couldn't find this one I don't know what
student of mine stole it but I highly
recommend you check out this series as
well the adult piano Adventures
all-in-one piano course book this one I
really like because it includes really
fun songs to play I do find the lessons
to be a little lacking compared to the
Alfred Series in terms of explanation
but the pieces are better so I like this
one better for explanation I like the
adult piano Adventures for the pieces so
if you can I would pick up both the
second type of Learning Resource are
piano courses and there are plenty of
great piano courses out there however I
can only vouch for the ones that I made
over on my website piano lessons onthe
web.com just like the piano lesson books
they introduce you to topics and pieces
in an order which makes sense for
beginners but unlike these they do
include instructional videos and you do
have me to email if you have any
questions and I'd be more than happy to
help you out you're also going to gain
access to notes worksheets and Sheet
Music around the pieces that you're
learning so it is going to help you not
only learn each topic but learn practice
and master them as well I have courses
for music theory ear training site
reading and anything else you would need
to become a well-rounded musician feel
free after this lesson to check out my
website piano lessons onth web.com to
learn more I don't want this whole thing
to be an ad for my courses so let's
continue so a quick question you may
have is Tim should I get the books or
your courses what should I do if you can
I would get both because again these
have great pieces to learn I don't have
all these pieces included in my courses
my courses have some different pieces so
this is a great supplementary tool if
you do decide to get my courses there
are a lot more websites and great
learning resources I have to share with
you but we're going to hold those off
until the end for now I want to go over
a quick list of equipment you're going
to need as a self-taught learner the
first op obvious thing you're going to
need is a keyboard now specifically what
should you look for in a keyboard well
the following 88 fully weighted Keys
that's what you want to look for and I
have a couple models I'm going to uh
suggest to you you want to make sure
that it has a foot pedal and if it
doesn't have a foot pedal you're going
to have to buy a foot pedal and you want
to make sure that it has inbuilt
speakers actually the fancier pianos
like mine this is a Roland
rd700 this one does not include built-in
speakers actually the the cheaper entry
models do include speakers and the
suggestions I'm going to give you
actually include those so 88 full
weighted Keys inbuilt speakers consider
that if it has them or not and then
whether it has a foot pedal or not here
are the two models that I recommend for
beginners so I mentioned a second ago
this is a high-end model the Roland RD
series I think there's an rd2000 now the
rd700 was like 15 years ago I got this
keyboard still works fantastic by the
way if you want a higher level keyboard
but some budget models you want be aware
of are the Yamaha and again see how it
says 88 key weighted action key digital
piano this is model P1 143b I know it's
kind of strange um and it does have
built-in speakers from what I saw um so
you can always you know do a control
find type in speakers and by looking you
can see that there is a speaker here in
the back listed as a feature another
entry level model is this roll keyboard
fp10 now this one's pretty comparable to
the Yamaha 88 key I've played uh the
Yamahas before I haven't played this
particular Roland model but I will tell
you that Roland is just like here's
Yamaha and Roland is Like A Step Above
uh Yamaha so maybe you want to get the
Rolland model but I do think that these
two are both pretty comparable
entry-level keyboards so again you want
to look through the features and just
make sure that it says 88 and it might
say hammer action same kind of thing
progressively weighted they like to use
all these marketing terms but just make
sure there are 88 weighted keys and you
should be good and this one does include
onboard speakers which is why I
recommend those two for those starting
out here are some things that you might
not have considered when purchasing a
keyboard and that is that you're going
to need a music stand again my fancy
keyboard from a while ago even the ones
today a lot of them don't include music
stands and that's because I think they
put all the money and research into the
piano itself and anything else they're
like well they can just buy it extra but
anyway just make sure that your piano
includes a music stand the two pianos
that I showed you don't seem to um I
didn't look really in- depth but it
didn't look like they did another thing
you're going to want to get is a piano
bench now question I get sometimes is
Tim can I learn on a chair to learn how
to play piano no you can't because a
chair if you look at your chair right go
around and find a chair a lot of chairs
even your school chair if you go to
school um they aren't flat what they do
is they start flat and then they kind of
like curve in for your butt I guess and
while this might be comfortable sitting
up and down and not really having to do
anything however with piano we are doing
a lot of pivoting uh here on your core
and if you sitting in a chair I was
testing this out last night I guess I
should have brought my chair back in my
office chair it kind of does bow in in
the middle there and it actually puts
strain on your back when you're doing
this you have to do this type of
movement all the time with piano and if
you have those two like sides pushed in
a little bit you'll actually feel that
kind of push on your back and it's not
as comfortable so believe it or not the
flat bench even though it's not the most
comfortable thing to sit uh when you're
watching TV is the way to go when you're
learning piano try to get an adjustable
one there's a lot of them that are just
kind of like one height but as you know
we aren't all one height this bra me to
another uh important point which is a uh
a keyboard stand right some keyboards
don't come with a keyboard stand you're
going to have to check the two that I
gave you if you want to get those to
make sure they do include a keyboard for
the keyboard I actually wish I had a you
can see it right here there's a stand
right here question I get actually I
have a fun story well it's a short story
when I first got this keyboard we didn't
consider about the keyboard stand you
know this way back my parents bought me
this for graduating high school actually
and we didn't know it needed a keyboard
stand and so the first few weeks I
actually played it on this table over
you can't see it on this office table
over here the problem with this is this
office table is a bit higher than a
stand would be stands are like a
specific height you can even adjust them
too which is great because we're all
different heights um so please get a get
a piano stand do not put it on a table
and please don't practice sitting in a
regular chair another piece of equipment
you're going to want to get is a
metronome a metronome helps you maintain
a consistent Tempo by providing a series
of annoying clicks and beefs that you're
going to have to play along to and I
shouldn't say it's annoying you because
you really want to have a good attitude
about the metronome this isn't something
you're going to be practicing with the
first few weeks but you are going to
want to add it in sooner rather than
later it really helps with not only uh
developing razor sharp Rhythm skills but
it also helps you identify problems in
your music because if you're able to
keep keep up with the metronome and then
all of a sudden you can't that means
that that measure or whatever part that
is needs more work maybe your fingering
isn't good and the metronome doesn't lie
it will tell you where all the mistakes
are you're going to need this as a piece
of equipment what the heck is this well
this is a tripod for your phone you put
your phone in here it holds it in one
spot and why is that useful well you can
use it to record yourself playing and
then look back at it which is actually
really useful not only in identifying
mistakes or slowdowns but also making
sure that you're making progress in the
long run because if you look at a
recording you did a month or two ago you
should be able to see a difference in
your playing and if you don't see a
difference well then you need to make
some adjustments to your practice
strategy the other reason I'm bringing
this up is you either want a mirror
camera or I actually would just use the
phone tripod um the reason a mirror is
good or having a camera on you is good
I'm actually very fortunate in this way
because I can see myself at all times
pretty much and the reason that's a
great thing is when we sit at the piano
the tendency over the many hours is that
we eventually start looking quite
turttly uh we start to turtle in because
our posture isn't good and by having a
mirror nearby or this you can double
check your posture just keep in mind
that as you learn piano you will get
better with your posture anyway but it's
only made possible if you have those
that mirror or the camera to adjust
accordingly and then another question
you may have is do you need a microphone
well maybe not like this but they do
make little microphones for iPhone and
Android which do improve the audio
quality a bit so if you're recording
just on your phone microphone and it see
sounds very muffled uh just pick up a
cheap microphone off of Amazon and uh
you can improve your quality a little
bit like that now this type of thing
which improves a quality a lot is uh a
whole lesson on its own and I'll real
quick I'll tell you how it works I have
my piano I have this thing called an
audio interface I'll try to bring it up
on Amazon to show you the cables go from
my thing into the audio interface into
my computer and that helps record it at
the highest quality uh it can and then
my my uh microphone also plugs into that
it's a baringer BH i n g e r audio
interface and that helps interface with
my computer if you want a whole lesson
on how to set this up let me know if not
I want to continue so let's get on to
the next thing next I'm going to teach
you about goal setting and proper
practice how to set goals so you want to
be setting goals every time you practice
in the first few weeks you may not know
what goals to set because you don't
really have any music knowledge to to
Really base your goals on but as you
start playing for the first few weeks
and we'll talk about the first few weeks
here in a little bit um after the first
few weeks you want to start making
specific goals on things you want to
accomplish during this lesson and this
is going to help you make a lot more
progress in the long run an example of a
good goal is work on measure 12 of
Moonlight Sonata it's a great goal
because it's very specific it's a
specific piece and it's a specific
measure of the piece probably where I've
been messing up a whole lot which is
usually probably where you want to start
your practice another good goal would be
like practice the or learn say you're
learning your scales for the first time
learn the G Major scale that's a great
goal to have it's specific what you
don't want is goal one practice the
piano goal two practice scales goal
three play a piece or two it's just not
specific enough and you you're going to
if you have goals like that you're going
to end up noodling around they call that
we're not really working on anything
specific that's going to get you ahead
you're just kind of wasting your time a
student in one of my comments
unfortunately I don't remember what
specific video it was but they were
talking about something very interesting
they were talking about how they gamify
their piano practice and what they do is
they sign points to every goal that they
hit specific goal and then after they
accumulate say you get one point for
each goal and then after over the the
weeks months they accumulate a thousand
points they treat themselves to some
sort of like I don't know they buy
themselves ice cream or some some treat
you know what I mean that it just gives
them something to work towards and some
people and students work really well
doing this however you don't want to
ruin it you don't want to be giving
yourself a treat every time you do
something little on the piano it's just
going to kind of ruin it so I would do
like a long-term pointbase system like I
said a point for each one and then I
would do it like every a thousand which
would take you maybe a year to get or
several months to get to cuz like I said
you don't want to be rewarding yourself
all the time but think about that I
think that would work for a lot of
students I did didn't even promise this
in the beginning but I want to talk
about five common problems that
self-taught students make all the time
and it's really tripping them up are you
ready number one skipping important
topics I'm talking about how to read
sheet music yes you need to learn how to
read sheet music Do not skip it music
theory Rhythm you'd be surprised how
many people kind of learn the basics of
Rhythm but then they don't really
practice it while they're they're
actually playing piano or practicing
piano um so any of that important stuff
like like how Music Works Theory how to
read music uh Rhythm the second thing
common problem that piano students face
especially self-taught students is
actually all do everybody does this I do
this too still sometimes you're
practicing too fast the tendency is when
we playing a piece especially one we
know right what do you want to do you
want
to play it full speed right off the bat
now I have played that piece before so
can manage that but slow down your
practice whatever you're playing now
slow it down a little bit even pieces
that were not familiar with the tendency
is to practice too fast and that will
end up causing you to skip over mistakes
and you're and not be as objective when
you practice number three I actually
mentioned this with number one by
mistake but that's not paying attention
to Rhythm you should not only learn
Rhythm but be actively counting as well
it's kind of a skill that takes some
time to get used to it's kind of like
playing with the metronome actually when
you first start playing with the
metronome it's going to be a nightmare
uh but trust me that you will get used
to it and you will be glad that you did
commic problem number four is students
are using things like Synthesia to learn
piano no no no no if you don't know what
Synthesia is it's like Guitar Hero where
these colored bars fall down you do not
want to learn piano this way it's okay
for learning like one or two pieces but
you're not actually learning piano right
it's like if I sat down next to you and
I said okay play this note play this
note play this note play this note we
did it like a million times and then you
eventually figured out oh this is the
pattern he's doing okay but did you
actually learn how to play the piece or
learn piano no so don't use anesia do it
the right way it's okay as like a
novelty or something but please don't
rely on it number five common problem is
too much pedal so the sustained pedal
you can't even see it unfortunately from
this angle but the sustain pedal when
you hold it down it sustains the notes
gee how crazy is that and it really is
useful
for chords playing notes separately as
arpeggios because the sustain pedal will
sustain those notes together and you can
kind of hear the harmony or chords a bit
better but what a lot of students will
do is they will do something like
[Music]
this ew you hear that
that that is because I'm holding up the
pedal too much and what's happening is
the different chords together instead of
having like a break between each one
like
[Music]
this The Petal bleeds them
together you can even hear it there it's
almost like if I took my hands and just
pressed all the keys at once so careful
too much pedal or not using it enough if
you don't know how to use the pedal
start adding it into your pieces proper
pedal usage actually adds a lot to a
piece and too much really takes away and
and and and students will use the pedal
I know your secret students students if
they didn't practice a certain measure
or something or or like they're they're
fudging it and they didn't take the time
to correct it they'll just slam down on
that pedal and play through it real fast
and they hope that the teacher isn't
smart enough to know but trust me we
know what you're doing up next are some
things I think that you should work on
as a self-taught student and then after
that I'm going to give you the road map
that kind of ties everything together
real easy for you but let's talk about
some things in your first few weeks that
you should be working on as a
self-taught student first you're going
to have to learn the layout of the
keyboard you're going to have to know
there a c e g a b c c sharp every note
on the keyword you're you're going to
have to know second thing is you're
going to have to learn how to read music
so not only do you have to know the
notes on the staff like that's an F
you're going to have to know that that f
is right here on the
piano once you learn about reading music
you want to learn basic Rhythm you want
to know that this is a measure of four
four these are four quarter notes each
one gets one beat 1 2 3 4 and I would
learn about all the common time
signatures as well like 44 2 4 and 34
next I would start learning very simple
pieces usually you're going to be
starting with a five finger exercise
going from C to G down back to C this is
what we call C position and if you're
wondering how are you going to remember
all this don't worry like I said we have
a road map here coming up by just
showing you some context here and then
once you learn some of those you want to
start want to start learning pieces in
order of difficulty how are you going to
find p pieces and Order difficulty
remember I have courses over on my
website piano lessons onth web.com but
this this is a great resource also and
then real quick some other things you're
going to want to work on are music
theory site reading and chords which
will help you out here in a minute with
to help you learn some of these basic
things I want to share with you some of
the videos that I've made that are going
to help you along the way and don't
worry I'm going to link these all to you
in a playlist at the very end of the
lesson the first lesson I have that you
want to check out is how to read music
in one easy lesson this is a lesson I
only put out a few months ago but it's
going to work you through how to read
music from the very beginning and
literally every strategy that I have for
reading music you can learn it in an
afternoon the next video I want you to
check out of mine is how to read basic
rhythms the complete version and this
one just like the how to read music One
introduces you to everything you need to
know about Rhythm at least the very
basics and it's really comprehensive so
by the end of that lesson you can learn
all about how Rhythm works you can do it
in like an afternoon the last and most
important lesson I want you to be aware
of is this one called how to learn piano
as fast as humanly possible again a more
recent lesson but this one I really
highly recommend you check out because
it's a sequel well sort of a sequel to
this lesson right I'm introducing you to
the things as a self-taught learner and
this actually really drills in a lot of
the things we're talking about today in
depth so you want to check out that one
and don't worry I'm going to include all
these in a playlist for you to watch
right after this lesson at the end I
actually want to tell you a story here
in a second but I want to give you three
really quick practice tips to ensure
that you're going to have more success
practicing number one block out the same
time each day ideally you want to make a
you want to make practice a habit and
something you do at the same time it's
like brushing your teeth right you
probably do it around the same time and
by making it at the same time each day
it makes it easier for your brain
because our brains are really geared
towards patterns and falling into
patterns and if you keep the pattern the
same it will help you out the number two
practice tip I have for you is to
eliminate distractions yes the house cat
that you have that always jumps up on
you you're trying to read play do
anything needs to be left outside well
hopefully they don't scratch the door
too much anyway or or any husbands or
wives just
I got to practice you know what I
mean I mentioned this earlier but be
objective when you practice speaking of
being objective it's story time and if
you've been watching my lessons for a
while you know that I always do a story
time or two in each video and here's a
story time today it's about being
objective when you practice so when I
was trying out for Westchester
University School of Music that's where
I went my teacher had a planned vacation
that he planned like a year in advance
like pretty close to the audition time
uh that I was supposed to do the
audition for Westchester and he was
pretty nervous going on this vacation
but like I said it was a family vacation
for him I didn't expect him to not do
his vacation for me but anyway he told
me he was like all right now when I'm
gone you have to practice and I hope
you're going to practice a lot and he
told me what the practice well I didn't
have a lot of practice time if I forget
exactly what was going on I think some
girl had me tripped up or something or
like I think I had finals going on but I
didn't have a lot of time time to
practice for the audition so what I did
was is I made a practice list of the
stuff he told me to work on and I really
sat down each day and I just nailed out
those things it took like 15 20 minutes
each day he told me I had to practice
for like an hour right but and I did
practice for an hour before but I wasn't
being objective so I was actually able
to boil down the lessons or the practice
sessions in much smaller time just
knocking out each thing anyway the
conclusion of the story is uh he came
back from um his vacation and I played
for him and he was like wow you've made
such a great Improvement what was your
secret and I said I was just you know I
wrote down the things you wanted me to
hit each day and I just hit those things
and that was it I was like I didn't
practice any more uh than I usually do
in fact a little bit less I didn't want
to tell him that uh but that's the moral
of story is that like if you're and I
got into Westchester University by the
way so if you are objective while you
practice it will make huge differences
um it's better to really focus in I mean
practice as long as you're able to each
day don't let this what I'm about to
tell you dictate your practice schedule
but it's better to practice 20 minutes
super focused each day than it is to
practice an hour just kind of like
noodling around and I was a teenager at
the time and teenagers in my opinion are
the masters of just noodling around do
you remember at the beginning of the
lesson that I said that there were more
resources I wanted you to be aware of
more books more websites well here they
are we're going to go through them quick
one is a site reading book series site
reading is being able to look at a piece
of music for the first time and being
able to play it by site now I could make
and in fact I am going to make a lesson
here pretty soon all about how to do
site reading properly but the one thing
you want to get is a site reading um
just like the the piano lesson books you
want to get the piano lesson books first
but you want to look into getting a site
reading book as well I love this series
improve your site reading it is by Paul
Harris you find on Amazon you want to
start with level one obviously if you're
a beginner but the great thing is again
they introduce you to site reading
examples from the very basic stuff and
then they move uh along in order so if
you follow the book series you won't
have any gaps in your knowledge or
playing ability by the way site reading
is one of the most important things you
can possibly practice the next website I
want to share with you is music
theory.net I love this website so much
there's lessons and but I especially
love the exercises so if you're learning
how to read music and you're like oh I
don't have any flashcards or anything or
maybe you're learning your chords and
you're like how do I practice this stuff
you know what I mean well you go here
and I have a lot of lessons on this by
the way that that introduced here and
here is basically a note reading quiz
you know and I can say oh that that's a
d and I'm going to find it on the piano
as well and it's just a great way to
practice all this uh rudimentary things
that I've been showing you that you
really need to know to learn piano
things like key signatures and music
theory and things like that music
theory.net write that down a very
similar website is teoria.com it's
pretty much the same thing but with
different exercises so make sure to
check out both and lastly on my YouTube
channel or a lot of YouTube channels
there are a ton of lessons that I have
so you want to click on the playlist
section and check out the playlist the
many many playlists that I have around
all these topics that we talked about
today I'm going to make one um at the
end of this lesson I'm going to link you
to and I especially want you to watch
that one but there are tons more on the
channel to look at so as I promised in
the beginning I'm going to give you a
road map that's going to kind of tie
everything we talked about together
because we talked about a lot today and
you need to make sure that your path
forward is crystal clear but before that
I just want to say a quick thank you to
all those that have supported the
channel over the years from the regular
viewers to the memberships to the
members to the mods to people that sign
up for the courses over on my website I
just wanted to quickly say thank you so
much without your support we wouldn't
have been able to reach nearly as many
students as we have so thank you from
the bottom and left heart now you're
here for the road map I promis and I'm
going to deliver and it's more simple
than you would think and and I'll
explain step number one get a keyboard
and all that equipment I mentioned so
you're going to need a keyboard a
keyboard stand you're going to need a
bench to sit on you're going to need a
music stand uh Metro Rome that you don't
need that right away but you're going to
need it soon and a piano book and or of
course and I just dropped something
sorry about that uh and one of these so
once you get one of these a piano all
the stuff you get to start you are ready
to start now you start by beginning your
course or just starting the book opening
the first few pages and and start
reading and playing what they're going
to tell you I ideally I like to go over
as far as you can get in a week you
don't want to push too far too fast and
one thing I want to tell you is like
when you first start learning these
pages are going to be super easy you're
going to Breeze through
them several Pages a week pretty easily
but what's going to happen and I'm just
letting you know this is totally normal
when you get to the middle of the book
right that's close to the middle what's
going to happen is you're going to start
to slow down things are going to get
more complicated you're not going to be
able to go as fast and that's I'm just
letting you know it's normal cuz I have
students that begin this book boom boom
boom boom boom we get through like 10
pages a week and then all of a sudden
they're like oh man I've been on this
this one uh I remember a specific
example but I remember a uh a student of
mine was really really distraught when
they got to the middle of the book and
they asked me like Tim why is it taking
me so long to learn this piece when in
the beginning we were just you know
rapid firing them off and it's because
that's normal and by the time you get to
the end of the book they're even harder
and it's going to take you instead of
going through 10 pages in a week it
might take you several weeks to get
through a couple of pages so just keep
that in mind I would only move on to the
next piece or topic once you feel you
have a grasp on what you're currently
working on work hard but don't rush so
number one was get all the equipment
number two was start on your course and
or
book number three then is to what be
objective when you practice again the
first few weeks you might not know what
goals to have but trust me but by
working in this book for a few weeks
you're going to start to know like oh
yeah I should really spend more time on
this thing I was struggling with so a
great a great way to find your goals is
think about like what have I've been
struggling with what could I be spending
my time on that's really going to get me
ahead remember to be specific as you can
uh you don't want to just be like oh
practice for 30 minutes I mean that's an
okay goal it's better than nothing but
you want to make sure and I told you
that story about how objective practice
can really help you so get the equipment
use the equip and practice objectively
is your road map to success yes you're
still going to reme have to remember a
lot of the other stuff we talked about
in that lesson but if you remember those
three core things it will set you on the
right path we're not done there's
another bonus section here I have for
you and then we're going to wrap it up I
promise after this bonus section common
questions I get I'm just going to Rapid
Fire them off as I see them do you need
a teacher question
one uh not 100% % however if you have
the money and the availability to get a
teacher why not I think it could help
you out or say you don't have the money
to take or the patience to take or the
time to take lessons every single week
you can just hire a teacher really for a
lesson here or there uh to help you out
when you need it so a teacher isn't
entirely necessary but if you have the
access to one use it number two how long
is it going to take to learn that's the
wrong question you should just learn
your stuff and just keep going that
answer depends is very different for
each person you can actually start
learning pieces though in just a few
weeks like like you'd be surprised in
just a few weeks you can start playing
like Mary had a little lamb you know
Jingle Bells some uh very simple stuff
and then to master piano it takes a
lifetime number three should I use
stickers on my piano people like to use
stickers telling them what notes or what
on the piano and the answer is no number
four how do I stay motivated try to
remember why you started to begin with
listen to artists and pieces that
motivate you and then three just
understand that learning piano is a uh
es and flows type of process where
sometimes you're going to feel really
into it like you love it a lot and then
sometimes you're going to feel like
quitting possibly in the beginning
hopefully a lot of that's going to
happen in the beginning just know that
that's a normal part of the process some
people when they fall out of love with
piano they think it's going to be
forever and that it's like the end of
their piano playing days it's not it's
just a normal part part of the process
right it's like being in a
relationship you know it's not all like
like super high up all the time you have
to learn how to navigate the bumps five
how do I progress faster you progress
Faster by practicing and being objective
and also I have a lesson here at the end
I'm going to link you I know I keep
saying it it's a lesson called how to
learn piano as fast as possible and I
want you to watch that lesson after this
one number six can I just learn to play
piano by ear yeah but not really to
understand music theory and the way
things work you have to learn how to
read music um now I do want to make an
important point if you're somebody that
only learns how to read music right
there there's two different students
really I find one that's like super um
it they understand like the reading real
easy the theory real easy but they don't
understand the ear training part of it
it's kind of two different parts of the
brain and there's some people that
understand the the ear training part of
it they can hear all this stuff but when
it comes to like stuff written down on a
page it's like no I'm not doing that so
what I encourage people to do is this if
you are a like Note Reader right I call
you note readers and ear trainers note
readers should learn more about ear
training and ear trainers should learn
more about note reading and you want
both of those skills to be as good as
you can moving forward learning piano
okay I have a comment that I want you to
leave down below by sharing the answer
with me it's going to help me understand
you as the student a lot better but it's
also going to help me make better
lessons in the future and the question
is this what is your struggle learning
as a self-taught student I would love to
know I think other students would love
to know so please just take a second or
a minute to let me know down below and
we have the final tip that we are now
wrapping everything up with are you
ready for it so remember before I
mentioned that there's a way to learn
piano as fast as possible we talked a
little bit about it today with being
objective but there's actually more a
lot more to understand about this stuff
and I have a lesson that I want you to
check out here I'm going to put it in a
playlist with a lot of the other videos
that I recommended today and if you have
some free time this weekend or today
make sure to check out all those lessons
and if you don't have time bookmark them
and watch them later your Pian teacher
Tim here thank you so much for coming
and I'll see you yes you in the next
lesson
[Music]
I see The Shining your